BALAKUMAR RAJENDRAN

San Jose, CA | <u>balakumar004@gmail.com</u> | Mobile:+1 (669) 275 3000



linkedin.com/in/balakumar-rajendran-55228219

Senior Network Engineer

10+ years of experience as a **Network Data and Security Administrator** with in-depth technical and process-wise knowledge in working across multiple platforms includes Switching and Routing, Firewall, wireless LAN, WAN acceleration, Load-balancing, SD-WAN, IP address management.

Technical expertise

Switching and Routing	Experienced in Cisco catalyst switches includes 9300 series, 3850 series, catalyst 6800 series, Nexus 9k, 7k, 5k FEX series with deep knowledge in TCP/IP model, multilayer switching, OSPF, BGP, MPLS, port-channel, QoS, STP, HSRP, NAT, VPC, VDC, software management and other layer 2 and layer 3 concepts.
Network Security	Experienced in deployment of Palo Alto Networks firewalls in Datacenter as well as in Cloud platforms like AWS, Azure, GCP and involved in migration from Cisco ASA to Palo Alto Networks firewall project. Good knowledge in IPSec VPN, Global protect, Threat prevention mechanisms, SSL proxy, HA, User-ID mapping and Panorama.
Wireless LAN	Experienced in 5500 series Cisco wireless controller and Cisco wireless indoor/outdoor access-points with technical knowledge in CAPWAP, flex-connect, guest Wi-Fi provision, wireless QoS and Ekahau wireless heat-map survey.
WAN acceleration	Experienced in Riverbed Steelheads, Interceptors and SteelCentral Controller with technical knowledge in protocol-specific optimization include SSL, file-sharing protocols, MAPI, cloud optimization, secure peering.
Load-balancing	Experienced in A10 networks load-balancers, a strong competitor of F5 load-balancer with knowledge in setting up load balancing between servers, source NAT pools, layer 7 protocols template, software management.
IP Address Mgmt. (IPAM)	Experienced in Bluecat networks IP Address Management with knowledge in DHCP and DNS service deployments, IP subnets allocation, DNS anycast.
SD-WAN	Experienced in Cisco Viptela SD-WAN, the market leader in SD-WAN with technical knowledge in configuring and troubleshooting WAN related issues.
Tools	Experienced in Netscout nGeniusONE and Riverbed Cascade profiler for traffic monitoring and reporting. Packet sniffing and analysis using Wireshark . SolarWinds NPM for fault monitoring, Cisco Prime for Wi-Fi performance and device monitoring.

Professional Experience

Jan 2012 to Present

Tata Consultancy Services

Title Senior Network Engineer

Client Name Agilent Technologies

Project Locations Jan 2016 to current – Santa Clara, California, U.S.

Jan 2012 to Jan 2016 - Chennai, India

Roles and Responsibilities

 Lead multiple roles including Network Architect, Operations engineer and Tech lead across my career in Tata Consultancy Services.

- My Architect role includes design, build LAN, WAN and secured network for Datacenter, new site
 deployment, migrating acquired company's network to our network standards, documentation,
 preparing topology diagram, move to production and knowledge transfer to operations team.
- My Operations role includes maintain, troubleshoot network issues in Datacenter and office
 environment, working with client or server/storage support team or third-party vendor, providing
 a permanent fix, document root cause analysis and update known error database.
- My Tech lead role during Nov 2014 to Jan 2016 at offshore involves managing a 12-member team, prepare reports and be in-sync with client management, develop process documents like Scope of work (SoW), Standard Operating Procedure (SOP), provide Service Improvement Plan (SIP), Business Continuity Plan (BCP).
- Part of the Enterprise **Change Management** team with good knowledge in change and implementation processes.

Achievements

- Upgraded our biggest Datacenter at Santa Clara from legacy Cisco and HP switches to Cisco Nexus series switches in core and distribution layer.
- Worked in migration of Cisco ASA firewall to Palo Alto Networks firewall at multiple locations and implemented GlobalProtect for employee's VPN.
- Expanded Datacenter as a result of acquisition of a different company and converting their network to our network standards.
- Acquired professional level training in Palo Alto Networks firewall, Riverbed WAN optimization,
 A10 load-balancing and Cisco wireless.

- Attended multiple conference and seminars from Cisco and other vendors including Cisco live.
- Awarded as **Star performer** TWICE for significant contributions and innovations in IT-Networks.

Aug 2010 – Jan 2012 Lason India Limited (now Exela Technologies)

Title Network Engineer
Project Location Chennai, India

- Lason India Limited is a publicly quoted business process outsourcing company with multiple branches across the world, serving more than 50% of the Fortune 100 companies.
- Part of the company's core network team managing its Data centers and end-user network across multiple locations.
- Engaged in designing and troubleshooting complex network issues by coordinating with end users as well as with company's other technical teams.
- Good experience in Nexus 7k, catalyst 6500, 4500 and other Cisco multi-layer switches.

Nov 2008 – Aug 2010 Dimension Data., (via Sequel Mynd consultancy)

Title Field Engineer

Client Name State Bank of India (SBI)

Project Location Chennai, India

- Part of network team supporting SBI State Bank of India's core banking project in Chennai city region. SBI is considered the top bank in India with the highest number of branches with more than 24k across India and other countries.
- Experienced in supporting networks in a real-time customer environment as a field network
 engineer in multiple bank locations where it is highly dependent on the core-banking network
 connectivity.

Certifications

- Year 2017 CCNP Cisco Certified Network Professional in Routing and switching
- Year 2015 ITIL Foundation certificate in IT Service Management

Education

2004 - 2008

ANNA UNIVERSITY - Chennai, India

Arunai Engineering College, Bachelor of Engineering in Electronics and Instrumentation Engineering